n
ah
[Music]
hello everybody and welcome back to the
ask abijit show I hope everybody is
doing
fantastic and before we begin let me see
who all is there on the live chat I will
greet some of you and then we shall
begin with the Q&A I can see bat first
gear
x uh Krishna ragunath from The Sur
Netherlands Anand Pai animish Danish
Khan pan Kumar Singh trupti pel rigin
rigin do Phillip geopolitical du America
is best akit Mr 88 Shri ramchandra
namaha runat the world teacher Banda
Panda super Rex feminist Slayer bries
SK uh goami
Akash geopolitical dub Vikram
geopolitical rajes rajash shran vatu
bries Vishnu mohanan man manka garage
Tour Master viwik Martinez the king
Phantom Delux Kush Abu drawing and art
kushu drawing and art an Pratap Singh
atira atti ugra t b moini Sharma jotna
rishikes Das Gupta Akash ba samb sh sov
tiwari nikil yadav sahil Das Gupta bav s
sorab Shukla prar Gupta anupam jwal
Surendra Gupta Abhijit m Chan
Deshpande Yash jadav sha johnv viang
Mishra MK Rajon super Rex Karthik but
Manu
Goa Sergeant Skyland crazy brain sandya
pran and so many other people uh so uh
yeah prai Paul drian Sandy 97 Karthik
but ainash and everybody else all right
GRE greetings to all of you I will not
be able to greet you all individually so
let's get into the Q&A and I usually
take I usually take geopolitics
questions first for a change let's let's
change things around and let's take
history first shall we so let's take
some questions about about history and
then we'll move to geopolitics after
I've done with a I'm done with a bunch
of History questions so let's go what's
question
one question one is by yaja was the T
desert ever always a desert if not how
long ago was it green okay the Thar
Desert let's take a look at the Thar
Desert for that we should uh take a look
at the map so where's the map here's the
map and here's the map so let's take a
look at where the tar desert it it's is
it's in Western India mainly the
Rajasthan syn region syn currently part
of Pakistan but you know what I mean
right
uh so let this load so you can see that
there's this big region over here that's
pretty arid and there's not much green
here right in the middle of the screen
so that's essentially the tar desert not
all of it is the sandy desert with the
sand dunes much of it is just arid
landscape but uh this region roughly is
the tar desert region now the question
that's been asked is was this always a
desert and if not how long ago how long
ago was it green
uh so I believe that the tar desert
became this region became desertified
about 20 or so thousand years ago during
the last glacial maximum so we recently
in GE geological terms have emerged out
of an ice age and the glacial maximum
the last one which is the peak of the
Ice Age was about 20,000 years AG ago
roughly and at that time if you go north
of the Himalayas we have the large
region which is Tibet and all of that
was encased in sheet ice all ice just
ice hundreds of meters maybe kilometers
thick
possibly so just north of the Himalayas
you had these gigantic ice
sheets and the ice sheets what they do
first of all the world was the planet
was very cold because of the Ice Age and
the ice sheets they would reflect away
sunlight and because of that for a very
long period of time there was no rainy
season in India for tens of thousands of
years no rainy season so because there
was no rainy season this place became
quite arid because of the lack of uh
lots of rivers in this region there was
only one major river that flowed through
this region for a long time and that was
the
Saraswati so the sarasa used to flow
through this but apart from its river
banks everything in the region was
pretty dry and arid uh so I'm not sure
when it was last green but it was arid
during the last ice age and then about 2
and a half uh about 2,000 BC 2,500 BC
maybe around that time the sarasti
started uh dried out to a large
extent and that caused further
desertification of the tar desert region
and now the sarasti only flows in
Northern India it's called the gagar
hakra river and it kind of dries out or
or flows into the Rajasthan desert the
th desert and disappears over there so
at some point in time it may have caused
created a lake kind of
thing with the drying of up of the river
as as it was no longer able to reach the
ocean as you can see here's the drainage
channel of the sarasti it's still
visible about 4 5,000 years after the
river disappeared but the drainage
channel is still visible in the
geological data so because the river was
no longer able to reach the sea it would
have created a big lake like structure
where the the Thar Desert currently
lies and that's what would have caused
the the the emergence of the desert for
example something similar happened in
the Aral SE so this is the Aral SE
region and if you look at the map what
does it say it no longer says the Aral
se but there ised to be a big sea over
here and the Soviets because of various
Agricultural and other practices I es
drainage practices they kind of led to
the the destruction of the Aral SE so
big giant Inland Lake the Aral SE
completely disappeared and you have a
desert there now where the lake bed once
lay this entire region was was big giant
Lake until the 70s and 80s 1970s 1980s
so once the the the lake disappears
What's Left Behind is a desert so
something similar happened over here as
well the tar desert so it wasn't always
a desert I'm not sure how long ago it
was green but I can tell you that after
the demise or the drying out of the
sarasa in this region the Thar Desert
this region became properly desertified
and pretty arid so that's the story of
the tar desert interesting question to
begin with let's uh take a different
question
now vickram geopolitical says why was
Australia being such a large continent
why was it still not discovered until
the 1600s the Chulas used to rule
Indonesia and Australia is not very far
from
there so when we talk about the
discovery of a land or a continent we
put ourselves in the shoes of the
Europeans right we talk about the
European discovery of the
world the Europeans discovered Australia
sometime around that time there was a
privateer or pirate called James Cook
well he's regarded one is one of the
great explorers but so that's the guy
who discovered Australia James Cook if
I'm not mistaken
he discovered it for the British and for
the Europeans does it mean it's the
first time humans ever discovered the
place first of all uh the native
Australians the Aboriginal Australians
the
original true indigenous people of
Australia they discovered Australia
about 60 70,000 years ago and they
settled there now they are not the only
people who discovered Australia so let's
go to our friend Google and let's ask
Google let's Google something shall we
here is the deal so Indian DNA
Australia very simple question Indi no
Indian DNA Australia so let's go to the
to this to the SC the to the Scientific
American
article open up so genomes show Indian
Indian influx to Australia 4,000 years
ago some Aboriginal Australians can
trace as much as 11% of their genomes to
migrants who reached the island about
4,000 years ago from
India and along with the their genes the
migrants brought different tool making
techniques and the ancestors of the
dingo the Australian wild dog if you
look at the Australian wild dog the
dingo it looks just like the standard
issue Indian Street dog so the ancestor
of the dingo came from India now let's
go to a different article we looked at
Scientific American let's look at
nature
nature uh CIS no option but to accept
their cookies all right nature
Aboriginal Australian genomes reveal
Indian ancestry the flow of genes
suggests the continent was not so
isolated after all Northern Australian
Aboriginal people can trace as much as
11% of their genomes to migrants who
reached the island about 4,000 years ago
from India and along with their genes
the migrants also brought more advanced
tool making techniques and the ancestors
of the dingo and they say these are
indan this is Indian DNA North not North
indiian or South Indian DNA H it doesn't
say North Indian DNA or South Indian DNA
it says Indian DNA which tells us that
Indian DNA is the same whether it's
north south east west so it's clear that
our
people discovered let's say Australia
way before the the EUR Europeans but we
are not taught this I mean this research
came out in 2013 today it's what 12
years later
2025 do our textbooks teach our students
about this no they
don't our textbooks are outdated
obsolete our education system is
obsolete anyway we will not go into that
so the point is Indians settled in
Australia intermarried with the uh
Aboriginal Australians brought in new
Advanced tool making techniques and
other other technology and brought in
the Indian dog so they traveled with
dogs
Indians and these dogs eventually became
Wild in Australia they became FAL and
they are now called dingos they look
just like the Indian dog and uh so so
forget so my point is let's not see the
world through the eyes of the Europeans
shall we that's what is inculcated into
our minds because our entire education
system is it teaches you history from a
eurocentric
perspective so we discovered Australia
if if you want to call it Discovery way
before the Europeans and there's clear
evidence of that in Northern Australia
so let's look at the look at the map of
Australia since we are talking of
stria
so here's the map so you can see
Australia is very far away from India
and it needs it you need to go go by sea
you can do island hopping from I mean
you can you know travel by land from
India to Myanmar to suomi which is
Thailand to Malaysia presently Malaysia
into Indonesia and you can do a little
bit of island hopping and come close to
Australia but eventually you're going to
have to cross the sea so we don't know
what what route the ancient Indians took
to reach Australia but they did reach
Australia Northern Australia to be
specific and settled there so that is
what happened a very long time ago and
that's around the time about 4,000 years
ago is around the time that the sarasa
stri starts drying out and the the big
uh sarasti synu area which was densely
populated people start start migrating
out of it east west wherever so a bunch
of people go westwards and they they
settle in we know that they settle in
Northern Syria Anatolia the
miani they created the miani Empire they
were Indians this they spoke Sanskrit
they were Indo Arian in origin and other
regions as well westwards we have the
Advent of Indian uh cattle in the West
Asia region in in Egypt as well about
4,000 years ago and at the same time we
have Indians arriving in Australia 4,000
years ago interesting period of time it
looks like there was there was a time of
great churn in India so around 4,000
years ago there was a tremendous churn
in India the SAS is drying out it's it's
like something that's not happened in
thousands of years it completely
reshapes Indian civilization Indian uh
demographics the way people the regions
in which Indians have settled and this
migration out of the the sasti Sindu
Sindu
region and Indians migrate all over the
place so we know they settled in West
Asia Mithani Empire the Hittites they
were Indians the royalty was Indian the
aristocracy and the warrior class was
Indian and Australia as well so forget
about the Europeans we discovered
Australia a long time before
them geopolitical dub says is emperor
asoke mentioned in the Raj tarangini as
a follower of jism and why did he hate
the
aivas okay so the Raj tarangini is
a 1100s text 12th century text written
by kalhan who was a north northern
Indian Kashmir uh chronicler historian
so kalahan was a Kashmir
historian he wrote he write this text he
wrote this text the Raj tangim which is
a uh essentially a record of the lineage
of our King our our Royal fames Kings uh
all that uh it's a record of our history
and he wrote it in
Sanskrit and that's called the Raj
tarangini the flow of the royal
dynasties of India so uh in
this kalhan mentions ashoke of course he
mentions Ashok as a follower of Gina
which sounds like he sounds like Jaye
like his Jan he's he's being described
as a Jane in that maybe it's possible
that maybe the word Gina was used to
describe Buddha and the the Budd
Buddhist uh thing as well we not quite
sure it's a little confusing so yeah he
does mention asok is a follower of the
of of the
Gina and he also mentions that Ashok is
the king or Emperor who constructed
shagar so I'm not sure I mean Shri nagar
can refer to I don't know we know
there's one shagar in Northern India and
Kashmir uh but I'm I'm sure in the past
there could have been multiple cities
called Shri nagar so it's a little
confusing what's what's mentioned about
Ashok Emperor Ashok in the Raj tarangini
but yes he's mentioned as a follower of
Gina now I'm not sure how to interpret
Gina Gina either as being a follower of
the J or a follower of the bod not sure
it's a little confusing uh why did
ashoke hate
the
ajivikas the ajivikas were one of the
ancient uh philosophical schools of
thought of of Dharma one of the ancient
dharmic philosophical schools of thought
it no longer exists and we don't even
have their texts so their texts have
disappeared we don't know a lot of
detail about uh their
philosophy uh I believe that the
ajivikas believed in super determinism
you know the Big B I mean we'll not go
into physics but the super determinism
is a concept in physics in theoretical
physics that the Big Bang happened and
everything I mean we if you can
calculate the positions and and and
momentum Etc and moment positions and
momenta of all the particles at at or
just after the big
bang then you can calculate everything
that happens in the future with a little
bit of uncertainty thrown in uh so
that's super determinism and the
uncertainty is purely random it's
quantum mechanical so that is the super
determinism of physics now the arjas had
this concept of super determinism that
everything is determined at in the
beginning and there is no free will
whatever we are doing right now is all
has already been determined the past
present and future are already
determined and there is no free will U
they believed in the existence of the
Atma soul and it was but they did not
believe in God perhaps so that's the
kind of
uh philosophy they had they also had an
atomic theory uh so vosik probably
borrowed atomism perhaps from ajiva I'm
not
sure uh now it is said that uh asok uh
persecuted the ajivikas and had several
thousand of of them executed I'm not
sure how true this is but one hears this
this uh claim being made not sure what
the basis of the claim is I'm not going
to research it right now um it is said
that
apparently somebody made a derogatory
drawing or or representation of gutam
Buddha as bowing down to one of the
leaders of the ajar or something like
that and maybe that enraged ashoke and
that's why he had several thousand of of
them killed that's one possibility
another possibility is that maybe it was
a political thing maybe the ajas had
thrown their weight behind his political
opponents which was which which would
which would have been one of his
brothers or half brothers that's another
possibility the third possibility is
that this never happened because we know
that in if you go to Bihar okay in
eastern India and there is something
called the barabar caves complex the
barabar
caves and these caves I mean it's it's
not just these caves were not
built in a single go uh it is beli that
Ashok built one phase of the caves and
his one of his descendants dashar I
believe Dhat Maia built another phase or
another section of the caves and there
are inscriptions that you know lend
Credence to this
Theory these caves are used by the
ajivikas so why would Ashok build caves
for the ajivikas if he was their enemy
and if he hated them so you know it's
yeah so it's a little confusing and we
not quite sure what the truth is I'm not
sure if it's true that Emperor Ashok uh
persecuted the ajivikas and the ajivikas
did continue as a sect as a
philosophical school of thought of of
the dharmic umbrella well into the Gupta
era the Gupta era is about 4th Century
to six seven 6th Century roughly ad more
or less give or take look it up exact
what the exact dates are so they existed
during the Gupta era the Golden Age of
India and they may have existed beyond
the 10th Century ad also Perhaps Perhaps
but today uh the the ajika philosophy no
longer exists nobody follows it and
nobody even knows the details of it
right so yeah when it comes to ancient
history there's a lot of there's a bit
of ambiguity and a bit of uh yeah that
sort of thing so we're not quite sure if
AOK actually really hated the aikas and
if he really did persecute them or
not Krishna runat from surami
Netherlands says uh recently
archaeologists from Southern India have
discovered and confirmed
that the Iron Age in the subcontinent is
older than 3,000 BC what do I think
about this I think it's not surprising
and I think it's wonderful that we have
discovered something new for a change in
India from the archaeological
perspective so it was well known for
quite a
while uh that uh Crucible
steel was being forged in Southern India
uh at least around 500 BC maybe probably
before that so Crucible Ste Ste is is
also called cak steel or W steel or
Damascus steel because Damascus used to
import the steel ingots from India and
then make Damascus swords from that so
the westerners named it Damascus steel
but it came from
India so this steel you need a very
specific technique and maybe the
technique was lost or is lost but you
need a very specific technique you want
to what see what this steel looks like
like it's very interesting let's let's
uh Google
this
um let's go to our friend
Google and let me put that on the screen
okay
wots
steel so if you look at the kind of
Steel it is I mean it's got a very
distinctive
pattern as you can see there are lots of
examples of this it's got a very distin
inve
pattern and this uh The Crucible steel
from ancient
India so there you have it that's the
kind of pattern you get from this steel
and it was very highly prized in the
ancient world it's still prized today I
mean uh the people have recreated
probably the technique but the original
technique probably is lost because the
British de-industrialized India during
their 250 years of occupation of our
land
uh anyway so we know that ws steel or
cic steel or Indian Crucible steel was
being forged at least around 500 BC and
probably the Iron Age dates before that
because you need to refine your
techniques to be able to forge steel
which is an engineering technique so now
we know that U the Iron Age is actually
older than 3,000 BC so not surprising
I'm telling you if we do archaeology
properly then we're going to find so
much more of our ancient history so so I
think it's wonderful I think it's not
surprising at all and I think this is
just the tip of the iceberg when it
comes to archaeological discoveries from
ancient India if we truly Empower
Empower and unleash the ASI or an
archaeological Department across India
we're going to find mindboggling
discoveries this is just the beginning
so
yeah okay the next question is by
yaja one was there agriculture and
cities in India let's say for 40,000
years ago second is it possible that
homo erectus or the ne Neals or the
denans engaged in agriculture and build
cities let's take the qu second question
first it's possible that homoerectus or
neanderthals or D may have engaged in
some kind of agriculture it's possible
we don't really have the evidence for it
but it's possible we know that Neal
burials have been discovered uh which
contain traces of flour pollen which
means that the individual who was buried
was buried and flowers were deposited on
on the body and around the body so that
is a very interesting ferary practice it
it shows love and affection for the
person who died it's very similar to
what people do today they you know Place
Graves on F I mean Place flowers and
Bouquet on
graves you put flowers on funeral PES in
India and that s of practice is common
today Among Us Homo sapiens the
meanderthals were our close cousins so
they also at this so uh that's something
that was similar that they shared with
us something similar with us and about
agriculture we don't quite no we haven't
seen evidence of that but it's certainly
possible about
cities maybe but we haven't discovered
any so one can keep an open mind and
keep the possibility open that maybe
they did maybe we had found those for
whatever reason but uh the evidence
isn't there now let's come back to the
first question was there Agriculture and
cities in India 40,000 years ago
okay let's talk about agriculture in
India and let me put U an article on the
screen this is an article by Dr Anil
Suri from 2018 one second let me put
that on the screen so this is a good uh
primer on how old Indian agriculture is
so let's just read a bit of this it's
common knowledge that food production in
the Northwest part of India of the
subcontinent began with the mear
Neolithic in the early 7th millennium BC
the 7 billion BC is about let's say six
7,000 BC okay uh what's less known is
that there are were many independent
centers of for the development of
Agriculture on the subcontinent there is
evidence of rice being used as food on
the ganga Plains from
13,000 years ago 13,000 years ago you
were we our ancestors were using rice in
the ganga PLS okay that's 13,000 years
ago um the banks of the Lura Dear Lake
in eastern utar Pradesh some stunning
insights have come in from there
um yeah so carbonized rise grains dating
as far back as 11,000 BC Etc were
discovered there that's that's what we
talking about
um uh so it looks like rice
cultivation actually emerged in India
not in China uh now what else do we have
we have more evidence of that Lura DEA
uh Wetland so uh Laur DEA Lake Region
had the Dwellers of this place had
progressed to Wetland rice cultivation
9,000 years
ago uh what else do we have okay we are
done with lur Diva now let's talk about
the oldest evidence that we have okay of
Agriculture so that goes all the way
down south to Sri
Lanka so and why are we talking about
Sri Lanka when we're talking about India
because at that time Sri Lanka was
physically connected to the Indian
subcontinent because of the age so it
was not separate as an island it was
connected to the subcontinent it was
part of the
subcontinent uh so there's evidence of
in the Horton Plains National Park in
Sri Lanka there is evidence of cattle
hering and grazing micro charcoal
indicating the use of fire to clear the
land of forests cultivation of Ed edible
plants and early management of barley
and oats from
15,500 BC almost 18,00 years before
today okay so that's how old agriculture
is known to be in India did we have
agriculture even before that so you can
check out this article there's a lot of
detail in this wonderful article one one
of the best I've seen about the
beginnings of agriculture in in India
you can check this article out uh so
agriculture existed in the subcontinent
at least 16 um at least 17 ,000 years
before today uh where was that yeah
about 177,000 years before today uh was
did we have agriculture 40,000 years ago
I'm not sure we haven't found evidence
of that we have evidence of Agriculture
40 177,000 years ago roughly before
today
cities what about cities uh we had
cities about 10,000 11,000 years before
today uh we have evidence from the uh
Gulf of hambat archaeological complex
and other other places other such places
in Southern India as well on the East
Coast uh that dates back 10 11 12,000
years before today underwater submerged
cities but 40,000 years ago I'm not
quite sure all
right yka says in 6,000 BC where
Southern India Eastern India and Tibet
mostly inhabited by pre-agricultural
hunter gatherers devoid of cities so
it's kind of continuation of the
previous question uh so like I showed
just now we had agriculture the
beginnings of agriculture in India in
the subcontinent about roughly 17,000
years before today you had management of
barley and oats cultivation of Ed edible
plants and so on about 177,000 years ago
before in present day Sri Lanka when it
was connected to the Indian subcontinent
joined to the subcontinent there was no
Gulf in between
so so clearly these were not hunter
gatherers that lived in the subcontinent
at that time 6,000 BC is pretty I think
the Riga was probably written around
that time because that's when the uh the
the Indian rainy season starts declining
monotonically and the Saras starts
gradually shrinking as a river around
6,000 BC is where this where this
happens so clearly the rig weather was
was written closer to 6,000 BC than to
1500 or 2,000 BC so we clearly were not
a hunter gatherer Society at the time we
were a pretty Advanced Society uh now
what about was ancient India of this
time 6,000 BC devoid of cities so let's
let's take a look at cities let's talk
about cities let's let's go to Google
and uh and what about ancient Indian
cities from that time so one qu one
one piece of evidence is this let's go
to p
poar uh underwater
so check this
out um the Hindu says ancient Port this
is a report from from 2023 ancient Port
City of pumar traced under sea a huge
Harbor Lighthouse and settlements formed
part of the Port
City
uh so this ancient city is buried under
it's not buried under sea it's submerged
under sea at a depth of about 50 to 100
m 30 to 40 km off the coast of present
day pumar um in Tamil Nadu it's not far
from pondicheri for example okay so this
dates back how far it dates back at
least 10,000 years now it doesn't say it
here let's see here Times of India it
may be over 15,000 years old it's it's
100 approximately 50 to 100 meters under
the ocean that's pretty
deep so maybe that it was the last time
it was above water could have been at
least at least 10,000 years ago so very
ancient city they have discovered
okay um so yeah it's so it may also have
been called cavari
patam so very ancient city of the coast
of the east coast of India of of the
coast of Tamil Nadu now let's talk about
the
uh
um combat archaeological
uh of
archaeology
complex okay so this is
um discovered in the Gulf of humbat so
you have another underwater city okay
and it's not just one city it's an
entire complex network of cities that is
about I don't know how many meters
underground Maybe 50 to 100 30 40 m
underground uh about 20 km from the
Gujarat coast and so on so I'll not go
into the details right now but this also
is at least about 10,000 years old
probably 11 12,000 years old so we had
cities an entire archaeological entire
complexes of cities long long before
6,000 BC if you look at these cities
that are underwater especially in the
Gulf of kbat region the dwarka we have
anci dwarka as well we find that they
are laid out like harapan cities grid
you know streets laid out in an AR in in
a grid system like what you have in
Manhattan today that sort of thing but
you had that 10,000 years before today
11 12,000 years before today so that
kind of tells you what kind of History
India really had and much of it is lost
and we need to start recovering that
through the through archaeology what
else um so yeah I hope that answer the
question one second where are we here we
are okay next question is by rajor gon
uh the question is is it possible for a
kingdom or a country or an Empire to be
very strong and not have expansionist
Tendencies are you aware of any such
rulers in history who became very
powerful but never expanded beyond the
borders they
inherited interesting question and
uh yeah so the point is this uh
there have been examples of of Kingdoms
uh and Empires that have not been
expansionist so one example I can think
of is the the Ming Dynasty uh in China
so this
was 1300s to about 1600s okay the Ming
Dynasty and this is the dynasty that
built the Wall of China the Great Wall
of China or at least it aggressively
expanded the Wall of China I'm not sure
who ini
built the beginnings of the Great Wall
of China but the Ming Dynasty uh it
rebuilt the wall of Wall of China and
fortified it
considerably um so the Ming Dynasty
essentially was a successor of of the
Yuan Dynasty the dynasty of sh chingis
Khan who had conquered China and it was
ruled by later it was later ruled by uh
sh kubl Khan uh so the successor dynasty
was the Ming Dynasty
and they became quite powerful but they
never expanded they instead they
fortified the Wall of China and they
rebuilt it so they want they were kind
of you know they did not want to expand
they wanted Outsiders to stay out so
that's an example of a of a strong a
pretty powerful uh
country or or or Empire because it was
an Empire the main Dynasty which did not
have expansionist tendencies isn't that
interesting now next to China east of
China we have Japan so Japan for a long
period of time had this
isolationist policy under the Tokugawa
shunet which is 14th century to 19th
century and it ends the Tokugawa shunit
ends with the mai restoration which
totally transform Japan so during the
Tokugawa shunit that period of time
Japan had Japan was quite powerful but
they
prioritized internal order and peace and
prosperity and they did not want to to
interact with the outside world so they
closed off the country they limited
foreign influence as far as far as
possible foreign uh contacts as far as
possible and they Japan remained a
closed country kind of like well not
like North Korea it was very different
but yeah closed off to the to the to the
rest of the world despite being a pretty
powerful uh country
militarily so that's an example you can
I can give examples of the Byzantine
Empire Switzerland is an example
Switzerland the Swiss Confederacy 16th
15th century onwards was pretty strong
for its well known for its military
strength uh Swiss mercenaries were
highly sought after in Europe so the
Swiss had a strong military but the
Swiss focused on being defensive and
they focused on being neutral so the
Swiss are are renowned for being a
neutral country so the Swiss never never
ever thought about territorial expansion
so I'm sure there are more examples I
mean we are an example aren't
we I mean when let's say ashoke Emperor
ashoke conquered the whole
subcontinent he could have gone beyond
the
subcontinent he certainly was powerful
enough to do that he was he was
militarily really powerful probably the
most powerful military in the world at
the time uh during ashok's time but once
he had the entire subcontinent uh under
control under under uh his governance he
said that's that's enough for me now I'm
going to focus on governance and he did
not expand beyond the
subcontinent uh so there are many
examples like this and there are many
various reasons why
uh why Empires sometimes choose not to
be expansionist multiple reasons each
example I've given had different reasons
probably the Ming Dynasty they they were
they were trying
to they they had these memories very
recent memories of the Mongol occupation
and they did not want to get entangled
with foreigners again so that's why
because of the trauma that China
suffered under the Mongol
occupation maybe that's why they became
um defensive in nature despite being
powerful militarily the Japanese
had probably different set of reasons
and so
on uh Krishna ragunath from the
surinamese Netherlands says although
Bangladesh and Pakistan differ a lot
from India and Nepal on religious and
political level but there are cultural
similarities such as language music
dance clothing Cuisine what's my view on
this my view on this is very
straightforward we were those same
people if you subtract religion from
East and West Pakistan I mean Bangladesh
and Pakistan then what's left what's
left is Indians the
same they're the same people right if
you subtract if you take religion out of
Bangladesh and Pakistan it's the same
people they're just Indians the same
Cuisine the same clothing the same taste
in music the same love for dancing the
same respect shown to Elders all the
same things are
there the only difference today is
religion uh Afghanistan is slightly
different it's been it was the first
part of the first region of India to
fall to the to the Turks and
Afghanistan's demographics have been
reengineered but if you look at pashun
culture once again it's just Indian
culture if you subtract religion if you
take religion out they're also just like
us so not surprising at all we are the
same people genetically but DNA doesn't
matter what really matters is
culture okay now let's take some
geopolitics questions shall we
okay all right okay yes yes a very
popular question us Aid Kiran motra PR
Paul and Kiran motra
again Donald Trump dismantled us Aid so
what could be the alternative to this
how do view how do you view the US Aid
funding pause and outrage from its
beneficiaries with Trump and musk
portraying themselves as exposing and
cleaning the system is it really a
takedown or have they already built
something more powerful in house perhaps
AI to replace it would they truly
dismantle an asset like us Aid without a
larger strategy in pay us Aid was one of
the most important uh things for the US
power projection activities and to
achieve various objectives now Trump has
shut it down what could be the its
alternative in the
future so would you if you have this
powerful tool at your disposal would you
dismantle it why would you do that yeah
you would do it only if it is not
serving the the purpose and it's
actually harming
you that's the only reason why you would
do such a thing if it's a very powerful
tool for your foreign policy for forting
unrest around the world for
destabilizing countries for carrying
carrying out regime change for for
spreading your culture and your values
around the world why would you dismantle
it right that's a question so clearly
there's a
reason why this was done and probably it
was not serving the purpose maybe it was
harming maybe maybe Trump's regime or
maybe the US in some way so we know that
um usaid was a left leaning organization
it had been taken over by lefties which
essentially means
Democrats and now the Republicans are in
power and this was completely run by the
Democrats that's what it looks like
absolutely no conservatives or
Republicans in usaid so that's why Trump
has dismantled it now it's not like it's
the only tool they have in their foreign
policy toolkit for destabilizing
countries and and infiltrating countries
and doing things like that it's not the
only tool they have they have so many
other such organizations the N National
Endowment for democracy what a wonderful
sounding name that's another another
such organization they have for carrying
out the same
activities you know industrial scale
Christian conversions and regime change
operations and and uh you know creating
a class of traitors in a country who
will work for the us against the
interest of their own country and so on
infiltrating
Academia all these things so that's the
the National Endowment for democracy
then you have the Ford Foundation you
have the Rockefeller Foundation you have
George Soros and his entire bunch of
things um you have
Oxfam and so much more so they've got a
whole whole
array of other organizations that can do
the same things so they would not shoot
themselves in the foot would they the
Americans no there was a reason for this
uh so there'll be outrage from its
beneficiaries and so on but those
beneficiaries that really matter to the
US they will be taken care of
their funding and their their uh
whatever benefits they were getting from
the US will be rerouted through some
other
organization okay uh so yeah so USA the
the dismantling of USA doesn't mean that
un US foreign policy is going to
completely take a 180 degree U-turn no
it doesn't mean that it's just house
cleaning and it's about making see what
they're doing is they're making the US
governance and foreign policy or
Machinery Etc they're making making it
leaner and meaner and much more
effective so they're going to cut out
the bloat by getting rid of these
useless organizations or
counterproductive organizations and
they're going to then rechannel all
those energies and and everything else
into other organizations and it's going
to get even more dangerous for for uh
The Targets target
Nations Vikram geopolitical says what
effect Will trump shutting up us Aid
what effect will it have countries like
Bangladesh and Pakistan Will trump
support the unus regime the way Biden
supported
uh considering unus history with Trump
okay look us Aid us Aid is an
organization was an organization it's
been shut down it's essentially been
shuttered so
it's it's been shut off the money that
was flowing into all the
countries has been shut down okay um so
us Aid activities in all nations have
been shut down not just Bangladesh and
Pakistan the Indian media is it reports
things selectively oh Trump has shut off
Aid to Bangladesh and Pakistan that's
not the case he has shut off Aid to
everybody which is flowing in through
this one organization called us Aid it
doesn't mean everything else will be
shut down so pleas and and it doesn't
mean it's only for Bangladesh and
Pakistan and he's a great friend of
India I don't know why the Indian media
does this to get get views and clicks
you'll do anything
right so uh the question is what happens
to Bangladesh and Pakistan now Trump may
not be a great fan of yunus because
yunus was a Soros guy he was a great
friend of the clintons and Obama
Etc uh the
Obama's it's I think it's the Obama
regime that awarded him the Nobel Prize
no the Nobel Prize is a reward given by
the West to its nice little good boys
and puppets and minions the Nobel Peace
Prize at least so it was given to him by
the by the Obama
regime so that's so he so he's a great
friend of the Democrats you know I'm
sure Trump won't like that very much
but having a
puppet of assal in Bangladesh is
definitely great for the us because it
gives them great amount of Leverage or
us or
India you know the US can unleash Mayhem
India or at least try to do that in a
variety of ways from Bangladesh if you
have an anti-india regime in Bangladesh
why would you give up an asset like that
why would you undo what you spent so
many years creating in Bangladesh why
would you undo that I don't see much of
a change happening in Bangladesh it it
all depends on how we deal with Mr Trump
what we offer him what he offers us in
exchange how we negotiate and so on but
I don't see him getting rid of of the
this great leverage he
has the same goes to Pakistan so you
know if
if USS us Aid has been shut down that
doesn't mean anything they will if they
need to Route money into Pakistan and
Bangladesh they can do it through 50
other organizations so I don't see
Trump uh you know being okay with unus
being removed and let's say
hypothetically shika coming back the
Americans will not want that to happen
it's great to have multiple sources of
Leverage against a big country like
us uh so yeah it makes no as far as I
can see it's not going to make a huge
difference TR Paul says with BBC Media
action admitting that 8% of its income
came from the U from US Government
funding how does this affect the
perception of Free Press and media
neutrality does the pause in USA funding
expose deeper dependencies in Could This
reshaped Global media
narratives okay
interesting
wording um yeah so it's it's uh it's
been revealed now it's emerged now that
BBC was getting 8% of its funding from
US Government from us Aid so are is
anyone
surprised I've been saying this for
years I believe that the UK is an
American
vasal ever since uh Tony Blair came to
power as UK the prime minister of the UK
the UK has been America's pet
Poodle right so obviously they will fund
their vels the BBC's talking points are
mere are nothing but American talking
points the BBC is an organ that furthers
American foreign policy so if they want
to say bad things about India for
example or China and let's say they
don't want to do it the Americans don't
want to do it themselves they will ask
the BBC to do it or they'll ask some
some other media out from in some other
country to do it or they will have 50
different media outlets in 50 different
Western countries do that and the BBC is
this great
old British institution aunti B they
call it right it used to be great once
allegedly now it's a tool of us
propaganda so absolutely no surprise
here at all as far as I'm
concerned uh perception of Free Press
and media neutrality there's no Free
Press there's no media neutrality
there's never been a neutral media
there's never been a free press it's all
paid
press this this idea of the Free Press
and a neutral media is the biggest
illusion the West has created there's no
Free Press nowhere there's no Free Press
nowhere in the world including back home
in India there's no Free
Press everything is paid for all
right okay next question
Shankar Karne and Mr
88 Trump tweeted that the Gaza Strip
would be handed over to the US by Israel
at the conclusion of fighting and
Palestinians would be resettled
somewhere else so where possibly could
all the Palestinians in Gaza be
resettled it's not a small population
isn't Trump Paving the way for other
countries to do something similar Trump
said the US will take over Gaza in in
Gaza do you think he will do that he's
literally inviting a war in the Middle
East and there's no way it's going to be
a peaceful transition or Le or
relocation of Palestinians how do you
see this
situation so yeah he tweeted that the
Gaza Strip would be handed over to the
US it will be taken over by the US and
redeveloped and then later he also put
out a statement that this will be done
once Israel is done with the fighting
and all that so Israel has to properly
bring peace in pacify the region um
sanitize the region or whatever whatever
language we going to use and once that
is done when Once peace prevails
America will step in and develop this uh
piece of real estate essentially so the
Gaza Strip is not a very small place so
let's go to the map and check take a
look at the Zaza strip yes uh where is
Gaza so we have to go to West Asia we
have to go to this tiny Nation called
Israel and here we have Gaza so it's a
it's not a very large piece of land if
you take a rough
measurement it's measure here from here
so about 45 km long and about 10 how
many kilm 10 kilm wide yeah so it's
about 500 square kilm which is not very
small it's not large
either so that's the Gaza Strip uh the
dimensions of the Gaza
Strip so what's going going to happen
and where will these people be resettled
if they if they are going to be
resettled so I hear that there are
multiple nations in West Asia that will
be
hosting uh refugees or or migrants from
Gaza uh Egypt is one of the Nations I
hear will is is likely to do that the
UAE and various other nations from the
uh Arabian Peninsula and I also hear
Indonesia is one of the destinations
possible destinations so it looks like
there are destinations for these people
to go through
not sure what the population of Gaza is
I not Google it right now but yeah so
there are multiple destinations look
when the US says the you going to do
this Nations do it so Indonesia is is uh
friendly with the US let's say okay and
the nations in the Arabian Peninsula
will also do what the Americans tell
them to do so it's not going to be a
problem to resettled to resettle these
people I don't think it's going to
create a war in the Middle East the only
protests will come from Fringe
organizations it'll come come from
Hamas hisbah uh Iran definitely Russia
and China as well North Korea sure but
not too many other nations will be
willing to uh condemn what's being done
and I'm sure the people of Gaza also the
actual civilians would be happy to move
somewhere else I'm pretty sure most of
them would be happy to actually get get
a chance to live somewhere where there's
not this Con
uh Warfare
happening um what happens to Hamas they
are entrenched in Gaza so I probably
mean that that would mean the end of
Hamas eventually uh so yeah there could
be a renewal in fighting and significant
uptick in in in the intensity of
fighting and hostilities before things
settle down uh so I don't think so so
yeah there may be fighting it may not be
a very peaceful transition of of and and
relocation
uh but uh looks like the writing is in
the wall it it you may see a phase a
period of time when where there
significant fighting in Gaza because
Hamas will not allow this to happen you
know they'll not just take it lying down
they'll
fight uh but I think the writing is in
the wall and once uh the people are
relocated the Americans will move in
into Gaza they'll red redevelop the
whole place
um so you may have casinos and Trump Taj
mahals and Mara Lagos in Gaza eventually
that that's what could
happen so we already know that there are
multiple countries that will be
potentially hosting these
people and yeah it won't be a very
peaceful transition of of
U Handover or the period before the
Handover but it's not it's certainly
something the Israelis can get done and
now that Syria has fallen in the region
and it's no longer um um an Iranian Ally
or Russian Ally it's going to be much
easier to take care of Hamas and hisbah
for the Western forces for Israel and
the
US okay next
question Vikram Ador says it seems the
next four years will be more volatile
than than the last four five years 45
years four to five years um Trump has
vowed to obliterate Iran if the build
nukes and so far he has failed to
fulfill his promise of ending the Russia
Ukraine war he said I'll end it in one
day right if the US manages to cause
regime change in Iran how will Russia
and China react because it's the sole
Ally in the region and that's not pro Us
in West Asia Iran is the only Ally that
is left for Russia and China in West
Asia only major Ally let's say Pakistan
is no longer a Chinese vasal it's now a
us vasal again after the 20 22 regime
change operation done by the US a coup
against Imran Khan so Pakistan is now a
US Ally us
minion and Iran is the only Ally that
Russia and China
have now let's imagine a hypothetical
scenario in which there's war between
Israel and Iran or Israel plus US versus
Iran in in the case of such a war do you
think the Chinese will intervene and
come on to the rescue of Iran not not
going to
happen let's let's look at the map to
understand the details where's the map
let me put that on the
screen so as you can see on the map see
Iran is west of India west of Pakistan
and Afghanistan west of the subcontinent
as you can see China's pretty far
away and between China and Iran you have
essentially us proxies Afghanistan and
Pakistan Tajikistan Gan usbekistan
turkistan essentially are part of the
Russian sphere of influence so Russia is
closer geographically to Iran than China
but in case there's a war between the US
and Israel versus Iran even Russia will
not be in a position to intervene
because it would mean that Russia and
the US are directly engaged in Warfare
which is a situation nobody
wants so if Iran is faced with the
prospect of war against Israel in the US
it's on its own Russia and China May
Supply it with weapons and whatnot as
far as they can but they won't be able
to come and intervene and send soldiers
and troops and so
on uh so yeah it's a dangerous period of
time for Iran and they are very worried
about Israel Israel has advanced
aircraft they're very worried about a
decapitation strike that Israel could
launch inan out of no where they appear
and just wipe out the leadership in
thean end end of story regime
change and yeah
so I'm not sure
if this would happen I hope War doesn't
happen we don't want war and we don't
want a complete change in the balance of
power in the
region
uh but yeah this is definitely a
possible a scenario that's
possible yeah you know Israel has been
Israel has always regarded Iran as as a
big danger to them and it's possible
that Iran may have made significant
progress on the nuclear front uh it's
possible they may have four to five to
10 nuclear warheads by now it's quite
possible and they have been making
progress on the uranium enrichment front
and they have built facilities deep
underground where it's difficult for
Bunker Buster bombs to
penetrate um so what Iran would need
from its perspective from from the tan
government's
perspective the only thing that can
ensure its survival
is is nuclear weapons and the means to
deliver them they can't deliver nuclear
weapons to the us obviously the US is
too far away the Iranians don't have
ICBM technology intercontinental
ballistic missile technology but they
have very very high quality cruise
missiles and uh ballistic missiles that
can reach
Israel and if they can guarantee that an
Israeli strike
will invol will invite nuclear
retaliation then that can prevent war
from
happening uh so maybe they have made
some indications the the Iranians that
they have nuclear weapons maybe a couple
of earthquakes that happened in Northern
Iran may have been artificial
earthquakes caused by the detonation of
a nuclear device it's possible and they
have already demonstrated the Iranians
that they can strike at Israel with
large quantities of of various kinds of
missiles including ballistic missiles
and cruise missiles they have Hypersonic
cruise missiles apparently and ballistic
missiles anyway they re-entered
Hypersonic or reenter speeds and a lot
of those missiles that the Iranians
fired at Israel earlier last year they
hit
targets and you just need a couple of
those missiles to have nuclear warheads
to cause tremendous damage so the only
thing that can save you know that that
can guarantee peace from Iran's
perspective is they having nuclear
weapons and they conveying to T Aviv
that we'll use them if you try anything
nasty against us obviously this is a
very dangerous scenario because the
prospect of nuclear war is something
nobody wants so we in India we don't
have a horse in this race we don't have
a dog in this fight what I would say is
we need to uh emphasize and and we need
to exhort both Nations to remain at
peace don't go to war
so nobody should start a war don't do
anything
provocative Vikram geopolitical says
Trump ordered to resend uh sanction
waver on chabahar Port this could impact
the north south International north
south transport Corridor proposed by
India Trump wants to support the imch
India Middle East and Europe trade and
transportation Corridor instead so that
Israel can benefit from it so yeah Trump
I mean his administration recently said
that they are resending a sanctions
waver that that the US had placed on the
Jabar Port so they have sanctioned Iran
Etc but they are not sanctioning the
chabahar port because India is using
chabahar India is operating at least one
terminal in the chabahar port but now
the Trump Administration Trump
Administration says no no more
sanctions uh waivers for chabahar we
canot sanction chabahar so it affects us
now because we are operating chabahar
why are we operating chabahar okay let's
go to the map once again we need a map
to understand what importance chabahar
holds for us
India so here is the map of the region
and chabahar is in Iranian beluchistan
not far from
guad so this is chabahar Port let's Zoom
super deep let's put a satellite image
on this is on the macran coast uh and
this is the town of chabahar and this is
where you have the
port um I think this is chabahar port
and probably somewhere around here we
have um India operating some some part
of this some part of
this this is chabahar Port now the
reason this is important for us is that
it allows us to uh have access to
Central Asia via
Iran so when we were we have been
supplying arms weapon systems Etc to
Armenia we have been doing that through
Iran so it goes probably to chabahar
from from from India the weapon systems
and then they're transported through
road by road through Iran and delivered
to Armenia that's what was happening and
chabahar is important because that's how
we are able to connect with Afghanistan
so we can have shipments shipped to
chabahar and then they're transported by
Road into Afghanistan because we lack
direct access to Afghanistan and
therefore Central Asia because Pakistan
has cut that off from
us so now Trump says we're going to
sanction chabahar so India can't use it
anymore so he's hurting India's
interests um and he says no that's okay
you you can't use chabahar but you can
use this new thing which will construct
in the next 10 15 years the iMac the
iMac doesn't exist it exists only in
paper thus far and for it to be fully
constructed will take at least a decade
so and obviously that will go through
Israel and it will go through other
countries which are all us allies they
will benefit from
this but for the next 10 15 years what
do we do nothing right and uh yeah so
that's the deal so this is another
pressure tactic that Trump is applying
on us uh because Mr Modi is visiting the
US in about 3 days so Trump will have
all these leverage points we have the
Unice regime in Bangladesh that we can
use against you we have the Pakistani
regime which is our Minion or puet or
wasal which we can use against you we
are now sanctioning chabahar so that is
something we are using against you so we
have all these pressure points and other
things against you and here are my
demands for you you got to do it for me
and then I will maybe give you something
in return that sort of thing so it's
it's a a bargaining position that's
being that's been opened um so yeah
that's there's nothing much India can do
about this the Americans will decide the
Americans are the all powerful Nation
there's nothing India can do about this
right now and that's okay that's the way
of the world the Americans do much worse
to their own allies in in West in in in
Western Europe against UK and all I
think we are still a Sovereign Nation
unlike the UK unlike Germany unlike all
the EU or NATO Nations so we are in a
better position despite all this
pressure that's been applied and it's
natural for a much more powerful Nation
to apply pressure in a variety of ways
against Nations that are less powerful
so that's the game we've got to play the
game
right vickram geopolitical says the US
this us regime the Trump regime will try
its best to make India a vasal of the
US don't you think it would be
beneficial for India to become one
interesting position we have seen
countries like Japan South Korea and
some European nations developing and
growing rapidly after coming under us
occupation we might not remain as
Sovereign as we are right now but we can
get we can get us investments in Tech
which would be beneficial for our
economy interesting perspective and
position
interesting uh thought experiment and
talking point so um yes the Trump regime
will try its best to make India a us
wasal now is it beneficial to be us
wasal and let's take a look at some
historical examples of bonafied
well-known certified us veles certified
stamped us vs one is Japan another is
South Korea a third is Germany dut
land uh let's take these three examples
let's let's take the UK also as an
example okay so we're taking four
examples Japan South Korea Germany and
the UK four nations that are us vs four
nations that have us military presence
on top of them Japan and South Korea
completely thoroughly penetrated by the
penetrated by the US military more than
100 military bases on each country
permanent US military installations
there's a permanent US military presence
in Germany as well as well as in the UK
All Nations all four are under US
military occupation these are Bonafide
us vasal now um Japan did tremendously
well after 1945 after it became us wasal
after it came under us occupation
tremendously well Japan already had a
great technological base milit
industrial base that's how they were
able to do so well in sec in the second
world war so they already had that and
That Was Then Unleashed by the Americans
so Japan became a technological
superpower not military superpower
technological superpower the most
technologically advanced Society on the
planet and they became a gigantic
economy by the 1980s it was the second
largest economy in the second or third
largest economy in the world and they
were on the way to become the biggest
economy in the world in the 1980s they
were threatening to become the largest
economy and surpass the US in the 1980s
that's how far Japan had developed and
then the Americans who control the
Japanese government and Military and Eon
and economy they made some tweaks why
the bank of Japan and Japan went into a
decline and it is still in Decline since
the 1980s after the Plaza
cords the economy is in shambles Japan
is no longer a high income Nation it's
now becoming a middle income
Nation so that's what they did by
turning by tweaking making a few tweaks
to the economy the Americans were able
to ruin
Japan and that's not all look at the TFR
in Japan the demographic uh situation
the total fertility rate is one of the
lowest in the world a nation that
prioritizes slave like work you are born
to work and you will work your entire
life and the purpose of your existence
is to work as hard as humanly possible
that's the kind of culture work culture
you have in Japan and South Korea as
well and South Korea also the same thing
they also became a technological great
power a nation that was South Korea that
was under dictatorship for a long time
after the Korean War um even now it's so
that's a different story and uh even
their economy is not doing great right
now and even their TFR has is in a
shambles South Korea another thing about
Japan and South Korea South Korea has
been thoroughly christianized by the
Americans their indigenous culture has
been eradicated more or less Japan lot
of
atheism some Christianity lots of people
call themselves call themselves atheists
and lots of what you what the what some
people would call Western degeneracy has
been introduced into their culture and
Society
their traditional way of life has been
wiped out in Japan also you know it
still holds ja Japan still holds on to
its culture in whatever ways it can but
yes that damage has been done by the
Americans to Japan by introducing
Western degeneracy atheism and
Christianity okay by engineering by
re-engineering the demographics
especially in South Korea has worked
very well so Japan's economy is under
shambles it's its demography is is
facing a
disaster uh lots of people live their
life alone lonely and yeah there is that
and the same thing is happening to South
Korea when it comes to Germany they are
being
de-industrialized uh and Germany is
seeing wave after wave of illegal
infiltration and migration all being
engineered from Brussels the EU Capital
so Germany is being destroyed okay
through immigration through
de-industrialization in two ways so
there is no uh no great economy in
Germany used to be the the economic uh
motor that that drove that drove the
European economy no longer the case and
the demography is being destroyed
through immigration and the same thing
you can say about the UK the UK is the
world's moneya laundering Hub London is
the world's Financial Capital world's
money laundering up and the UK is a poor
Nation attached to London which is now
being destroyed demographically through
illegal immigration legal immigration as
well Pakistani grooming gangs are are
creating Mayhem in society so if you
become a US wasal you will eventually be
destroyed I'm not saying the US is bad
I'm saying you become a wasal of any
powerful Nation eventually you they may
decide to destroy you for for their own
purpose for their own
benefit so for some time maybe for a few
decades you will prosper your economy
will do well they will certain
industries to flourish and if you are a
wasal of a powerful Empire your
citizens are happy because they benefit
from it but the nation eventually gets
destroyed the culture gets
eradicated so I do you think it's
beneficial for India to have that I
think it's better to have a period of
next 50 years of
struggle struggling
alone and building up our military and
economic and technological might do that
for the next 50 years don't complain
every two years nothing is happening
it's a slow process but if you become a
wasal of the great superpower of the
Empire you will eventually be doomed
they will use you and then Chew Chew you
up and throw you out so not a good idea
okay PR Paul says how do you see PM
modi's upcoming US visit what do you
think is the significance of this trip
and what are the likely outcomes of his
meeting with Trump look Trump is in a
hurry and this is a completely different
Donald Trump from what we saw from
between 2016 and 2020 the first Trump
1.0 was a very different Trump he was
not allowed to do anything not allowed
to achieve any of his objectives and he
wasn't quite sure of his objectives as
well he wanted to build a wall with
Mexico he doesn't care about a wall
today right now he's in tearing hurry to
completely upend the entire world and he
his objective is to be remembered as the
biggest baddest greatest president of
the US since George
Washington okay and he has the full
might of the deep
state right behind him this
time so he's in a hurry he uh he has
completely reshaped uh the perception of
Canada and Mexico in the relationship
with these two countries he's now
focusing on Gaza which he will deal with
very quickly he's talking about
Greenland he may get that he's talking
about the Panama Canal he may get that
so these are the low hanging fruits
Canada push over he can deal with them
any any he wants Mexico once again
there's nothing Mexico can do against
the US so he can deal with them uh Gaza
easy to deal with from a US perspective
this this is all lwh hanging fruits for
him then comes India India is the
world's fourth fourth most powerful
Nation number four in the world India is
a nation that is neither here nor there
when we talking about taking sides we
neither in the Russia China Camp we
neither in the western camp we are
friendly with everybody we have a multi-
aligned foreign policy multi-polar
foreign policy some would call it multi-
aligned some would call it non-aligned I
don't like this term non-alignment I
would say multi-alignment
strategic autonomy is a term indian
analysts love to use whatever you want
to call it we have an independent
foreign policy that's what it means and
we're not taking sides with anybody we
want to deal with everybody in a
friendly way now when Mr Modi visits
Washington DC in 3 days or so from now
Mr Trump will be ready for him so they
meet and they have the customary
hug then they go inside behind closed
doors and that's where the where the
real game starts and here's what Mr
Trump will tell Mr
Modi look okay I'll not try and speak
like him because I can't do that but
he's going to give a set of
ultimatums I need this this this this
this from
you you need to decide right here right
now today not tomorrow not next week you
going to decide right here right now are
you with us or against us if you are
friends with China and Russia you're
against us so you have to take a
side that's quite likely what will
happen so it's so what does that mean
for us he if he gets everything he wants
it will mean that India will become a US
Ally India will cut off relations with
China and Russia and be completely Pro
West in a in a in an ideal scenario he
will even even want want US military
bases on Indian Territory now he will
come up with absurd demands to get what
he really wants you make you ask for a
100 billion and then when the person
says no you say Okay instead of 100
billion give me 100 million that sort of
thing so you make an outrageous demand
so that you can then later come down and
ask for what you really want and then
the the other side will be willing to
give it to you so he knows how to
negotiate how to bargain he has a very
distinctive style the art of the deal so
look we're going to be presented with a
set of
ultimatums and you know when the when
Trump gives you ultimatums he can make
good on those ultimatums and threats so
we can't say no but what we can do is
yes sir of course we'll do what you want
but here are the things we want
sir number one number two number three
these these things we also want so we
give you what you want you please sir
give us what we want and he said no I
can't do this that's too much you're
asking for then you negotiate and you
bargain and you you do that and ideally
we get as much Advantage as possible out
of what out of the entire thing so what
is it that we can ask for we can say sir
you have taken you are sanctioning
chabahar now we cannot access Central
Asia because we cannot go against the
sanctions sir we need access to Central
Asia please please give us guaranteed
access we will do what you say right so
what what is what is the meaning of
guaranteed access to Central Asia it
means po or balistan or something
obviously he won't give that but then we
we can negotiate then about about
chabahar the other thing we can ask
for is that okay sir you are deporting
Indian illegal migrants immigrants to
the us we will we will take them back of
course but sir we will now do the same
thing here we will send back Bangladeshi
migrants to Bangladesh so please don't
make a big deal of it we will take back
all our illegal immigrants and you allow
us to send back the godamn Bangladeshi
infiltrators who are who are infesting
India and you allow us to do that and
please don't make your media do a human
Cry of or this that's another thing we
can ask for third thing please stop all
this
all the all this support for uh
industrial scale Christian conversions
in India your missionaries and all these
organizations that are converting
Indians on a mil on on an industrial
scale demographic re-engineering stop
that please another thing we can ask for
is please end your support for project K
the cookie cookie terrorism in Manipur
please stop funding the cookies that's
it then we'll deal with the rest once
you stop funding them and supplying them
arms ammunition all that we'll quietly
de deal with them with the illegal
infiltrators so there are things we can
ask for in exchange for what they ask
for us they will
obviously Trump will obviously want
India to become a US
FAL um we can pretend to be a us FAL
with certain red lines one red line that
cannot be crossed is no American
military bases on American soil or on
Indian soil as long as that not there
you are not really a
wasal um but yeah he may said that you
have to buy our arms and ammunition and
weapons you have to buy the F35 the more
American weapon systems you buy the more
you get embroiled in in you know
infiltrated by them uh because you have
to open up uh your military to them you
to sign various agreements and all uh so
it's going to be a
process but Trump will have certain
ultimatums for us for Mr Modi so Mr Modi
will obviously be prepared for this he's
a very smart man and he will have to go
back he will have to go there prepared
with a set of counter demands and then
let the negotiation begin let the let
the game begin and the two leaders Mr
Modi and Mr Trump get along very well so
obviously it will not be it will be a
pretty uh cordial and polite uh
negotiation um of course this is a very
different Mr Trump it's not the old Mr
Trump this is a very different Beast
and you may be friends at a personal
level but this is between two countries
so he's not going to uh you know step
back so that's how it's going to
be I think okay I think the next four
years is going to see in the next four
years we're going to see The Pinnacle
the Pinnacle of the India us
relationship the best ever time we've
had in the relationship between India
India and the US all problem solved best
relations how good Mr Modi and Mr Trump
dancing together hand in
hand that's what I think will happen the
next four years we just get to need to
you know play our cards
right PR Paul again uh with China's dual
1.5 Pro outperforming major large
language models on benchmarks and
leveraging Moe architecture with seven
experts how do you view do this
development the global AI race could
this shift the balance of AI leadership
towards China and what should India
focus on to remain competitive in this
evolving
landscape uh okay the new Chinese
llm is apparently outperforming major
known llms on various benchmarks and so
on yeah does it mean that this the
balance of AI leadership has shifted
towards China absolutely not absolutely
not the US is the Undisputed leader in
AI okay uh I don't know what is the most
powerful AI system right now in the
world it's some version of chat GPT I
suppose now ai is branching out into
various domains certain AI systems are
are the are the best at coding other AI
systems are the best at other tasks and
so on I think the most powerful system
out there right now is deep research or
something by chat GPD by by by open
AI that's the American in the American
scheme of things but apparently the
Chinese thing is outperforming these
llms does it mean the Chinese have
stolen a march on the Americans
absolutely not why do I say absolutely
not because what you are
seeing in the US scene these various
systems that are out in the public
domain that's merely the tip of the
iceberg the
real what's really happening is all
behind closed doors it's all happening
in
secrecy I I can assure you they have
already achieved AGI artificial general
in intelligence and the moment they
achieve ASI it's going to be game over
the the the models that they have which
have not been revealed to the public are
going to be orders of magnitude more
powerful than the than whatever the best
model is out there right
now and the Americans have poured
hundreds of billions of dollars into
this and there's another $50000 billion
dollar coming in the Chinese have
haven't done that as far as we know
China is doing well inia no doubt but I
assure you the Americans are way higher
of China what should India do on this
about this to remain competitive no
first of all start competing it's not
about remaining competitive it's about
first of all let's try to compete let's
start something let's build an AI so
yeah the government has has announced
that we are going to have our own large
language model by the end of this year
good good so yeah that's the deal
okay uh chavda Supremacy in devashish
Kap why don't we have our own large
language model llm yet despite having
significant it talent and India Rising
as a global semiconductor Market what do
you think of India's AI Mission can
India build a large language model in a
year also the government has allocated
highest money this year for private
sector-led research so why don't we have
an AI system a large language model yet
it's because our uh private sector
despite having money and resources and
all that they focus on short-term issues
and profits and all that they don't
think strategically they don't think
from a geopolitical perspective look in
an Ideal World your entrepreneurs your
your business people Etc especially in
the tech domain should focus on Research
I mean should focus on Research first of
all we don't focus on Research we focus
on Building Solutions and providing
services so if you have chat GPT we'll
build a chat GPT rapper which uses ch ch
JP llm to provide certain outcomes for
the end user so quick you can make quick
money from that you know you can have a
bunch of coders programmers 5 10 20
people do it in in a few days test it
and deploy it rapidly and put out um U
um an app somewhere and then you make
money out of it so it's all about
shortterm short-termism
in an Ideal World you want people not
just to your your entrepreneurs your
business business your business people
do not just focus on shortterm on making
money shortterm but on investing in in
in in resources and research
R&D fundamental R&D but that's not
that's never been the approach in India
because of the the kind of culture
that's come into India from the 1980s
onwards of of Simply delivering services
and doing
Arbitrage labor Arbitrage and so on so
the entire Indian it sector because of
historical reasons has focused only on
providing services and providing
Solutions and making money in the short
term you've never had this long-term
hard-headed strategic approach never had
that uh so that's why nobody has
invested in this uh despite so that's
why we don't have any AI system on large
language model despite having as we know
one of the biggest it Talent pools in
the world and we're also Rising as a
global semic market that that doesn't
that's not something that
correlates uh but yeah uh now what do I
think of India's AI Mission so the
government of India has announced an
near Mission and it said Mr ashin ver of
the minister of it I think has said uh
that we going to have our own llm large
language model by the end of this year
and we have allocated some money for
that I think it's very feasible for
India to have a large language model of
its own by the end of the year one of
the simplest short cut is to take an
open source model like deeps carb or
something it's entirely open source take
it tweak it and and and uh deploy your
own model but the the problem with that
is that we don't know what kind of
data uh deeps carbon has been trained on
you can take the weights and things like
that but ideally what you want is to
have your own system you know developed
from scratch
and uh you feed it you you train it on
your own data set that's what you
ideally want so all you need for the
look that what you need to bre build an
AI Model A large language model is well
known today you get a bunch of bright
young kids between the ages of 18 to 25
get 20 of them or 40 of them or 50 of
them maybe 20 is enough you give them a
salary of one CR a month and you put
them in a building you that you get a
salary of 1 CR a month but you got to
stay in the building until this is done
I assure you within 6 months maximum you
will have a high quality
llm AI system you're going to have that
it's easy you have to give them the a
salary that tremendously incentivizes
them and you have to give them all the
hardware they need which is the uh gpus
and all that whatever it costs it won't
cost a
lot so it's eminently feasible for us to
do that but you have to hire the best
talent you need to do that you need to
get the brightest people so here's a
problem that I am hearing about I'm not
sure how true this is I'm not sure what
the source of this information is but
this is what somebody has tweeted a
person called sayak Paul he said he
tweeted this to Mr Ashwini vnav why are
you recruiting folks who don't have a
solid technical knowhow of AI systems
and how they are built at a a large
scale stop going only via academic
affiliation and look at the actual
Hands-On stuff core contributions to
good Libs knowledge across the AI
Spectrum
Etc this is I don't know how true this
is but I would not be surprised if this
is the direction in which we are going
our bureaucrats our babo they only look
at academic affiliation and all the
status stuff they don't look at
actual ability that's always is being
the thing that plagues India we we look
at what degree you have and from where
you got the degree and what your grades
were but what actual skills do you have
what have you what experience do you
have what have you built thus far that's
what you've got to look at forget about
the degree what has the person built
thus far and what skills does the person
have forget about how old or young the
person is and forget about what degree
they may or may not have you've got to
find the best talent and the best way to
look at to find the best talent is to
look at what they've already
done what they've already built what
kind of portfolio do they have what kind
of track record do they have look at
their GitHub repository what they've
done on GitHub it will all be there so
that's what we need to do we need to
have people in the AI mission who
actually understand who are technical
people not bureaucratic people if you
staff it full of bureaucrats you're
going to go in the wrong direction I'm
not saying bureaucrats are bad bad
people you need domain experts and
subject matter experts who are handling
the whole thing top to
bottom and when they make when they ask
the the the ministry for x amount of
money that should be given to them no
questions asked don't have a whole
hierarchal structure of of 50 different
bureaucrats running running the show
that's the worst possible way to start
this Mission now I have a different
suggestion the AI mission is well and
good and they have that the government
is the whole thing itself great
wonderful we have iits and and and nits
across the country
right choose the best the top 10 iits
let's say Okay plenty of technical kids
over
there let's run a yearly competition
between the
iits Who develops the best llm the most
powerful most capable
llm give each i x amount of
money one chunk of the money is all
about the hardware you need so many gpus
all the hardware on which to run the L&M
and whatever other money is required
give it to each IIT the top 10 iits and
let them build their own team of people
who will work on this problem for one
year and hold a competition between
between the iits and the one that wins
give them a big cash price 10 crores
whatever it's peanuts for the government
of India 10 CR nothing it's it's small
change it's pennies for them so have a
competition and do this on a yearly
basis and each year the IIT needs to
build upon its success or whatever the
lessons they've learned in 5 10 years
we're going to have a thriving a AI uh
um what do you call it
ecosystem I mean is this so hard to do
so I I hope we do some of these things I
think it's very it's eminently feasible
for India to have in a very short time
high quality air systems high quality
large learning models and whatnot very
very feasible for us to have it I am
tremendously optimistic we can do it as
long as the leadership gets the basics
right all
right okay Indian stock picker says our
external Affair Minister external
affairs minister Dr J Shankar was given
a front row seat fantastic during Trump
during Trump's saring in ceremony but
later on in spite of inviting Modi G
this early to the US how should we see
this aggressive Trump speeches and
deporting 100 plus Indians like
criminals hands and feet Chained and
Silence from our side not no condemning
the way of deportation but e reply said
this is routine procedure of deportation
no change from past episodes how do we
see this aggression from us side and Etc
and and weak response from our side uh
so there you were saying that these
people were deported 100 plus indan
indans were deported like criminals
hands and feet chained um excuse me they
are
criminals these people are criminals
there you know there are various
categories of criminals and there are
various categories of crimes there are
nonviolent crimes so a criminal is not
necessarily a murderer or or or or a or
a burgler or something like or somebody
who does various kinds of violence
that's not the only types of criminal we
have
entering a country illegally is a
crime aren't we sick and tired of the
millions of illegal Bangladeshi
infiltrators in India haven't aren't
they all committing a crime by entering
and and residing in India
illegally that's a crime isn't it so so
if these Indians entered the US
illegally they are criminals and then
the country the US whose laws they have
broken and whose territory they are
residing that country will deal with
them according to their own legal system
and their own ways of doing things why
should we complain these illegal
infiltrators into the US of Indian
origin they have shamed our country they
deserve to be brought back in
Chains why are people getting upset I
don't get it I would like to see
Bangladesh is deported from India I'm
not saying treat them badly or whatever
get rid of them right they are all
criminals entering a country
illegally is a crime I don't understand
why Indians are all upset about this
thing they are criminals and apparently
there are many more such such
individuals in the US uh so let's let's
not be emotional let's be factual
criminals will be treated like criminals
don't be a criminal don't do crimes and
then you'll be treated well with
respect so I am I I don't see any
problem in
this Hedgehog's dilemma says uh Elon
Musk has rehired an employee who openly
promoted racism with statements like
normalize Indian hate in JD van the vice
president of the US who has an Indian
Indian origin wife he has also backed
this individual despite the lack of any
apology what does this indicate about
the perception of Indians among such
influential figures and how should
Indians respond to such attitudes um so
first of all
yeah this this uh individual this person
who was uh in the department of
government governmental efficiency Doge
uh he had tweeted things like normalize
Indian hate and so on okay and he he was
fired because of that but Elon Musk is
now rehiring him and JD van the vice
president has supported this he said
that look it's a mistake it's a kid um
everybody makes some statements that are
stupid and then later on they don't
agree with those statements because have
grown so I don't see a problem with that
that's what JD van says despite having
an Indian wife and kids half Indian kids
now imagine this scenario imagine this
hypothetical scenario in which an Indian
person makes a statement hypothetical
scenario hypothetical statement
normalize uh American hate or normalize
hate against ex religion or why religion
okay imagine this happens and then the
Indian government hes this person how
will the Western media react how will
the US government
react they will
unleash their media against us like a
pack of rabies infested dogs Wen they we
have seen this in the past if something
like this happens in India we will be
demonized for weeks and then we will
that sort of thing will happen but if
they do it then it's perfectly fine so
these people are politician
Elon Musk is also a deao politician now
and he actually has the benefit so and
and JD V is an aute politician which
it's now apparent it's now obvious is an
aute politician
when the democ when the Republicans went
after VI ramaswami because he made a
statement saying that Americans need to
have higher standards uh when the democr
when the Republicans went after VI he
was demonized and he was thrown out of
Doge J JD Vance kept
quiet despite ramaswami making a good
point JD Vance did not come to his
support of his
friend now there is
this this anti-india hatred all over the
place in the US anti-indian
hatred and then musk rehires this person
who said normalize Indian hate jdance
goes out and says I am okay with this I
support this don't don't make a big deal
of this so he is playing to the gallery
he knows where the sentiment of his
voter base
lies and he's ensuring making sure that
he doesn't alienate
them despite having a wife who of Indian
origin and kids who are half
Indian so yeah that's JD van he has
acted like a coward essentially it's so
cowardly uh thing that he has
done but what does it indicate about the
person ception of Indians in the US it
it it tells you my dear friends that
Indians uh despite even
though a person may have an American
passport if you are Indian if you are
brown skinned especially Indian
especially Hindu then you are a second
class citizen in the US so ideally you
should come back to India and build this
country and I would appeal to our
honorable prime minister Shri Modi G to
make India a place that welcomes people
back and treats them well and gives them
every potential every possible
opportunity to succeed that's what I
would request the prime minister of
India to please do I know you're already
working very hard in this Direction
please even more
please rakar Gupta says China has now
developed a sixth generation fighter
sixth generation fighter jets for its
defense while India is still struggling
to develop a fifth generation fighter
blame should India now focus on
developing indigenous made in bhat
fighter jets at a fast pace or should we
buy new generation fighter planes from
other countries like Russia in the
current
situation A Brief answer I'll give you
we should do two things in parallel
first of all keep developing jet engine
technology of our own and keep
developing the fifth generation fighter
plane that we are developing amca that's
the first thing we should do in parallel
with that we should also try and
purchase jet engine technology from a
friendliest
Nation whether it's France whether it's
Russia whoever we don't need to have the
best jet engine technology in the world
we need to have good enough jet engine
technology it doesn't have to be the
best in the world the Russian Saturn
engine that powers the suo 30 mki I
think that's good
enough if you can get that jet engine
technology and you are able to build it
entirely in India Game
Changer so that and purchase something
like the 57 or or
whatever but also get a full transfer of
technology and pay for the transfer of
Technology pay whatever they ask
for just get
it so then we can keep developing our
own systems and also have inhouse
production of these systems that's what
we need to do in parallel but if we
acquire the technology for jet engine
for a jet engine and for the 57 or
whatever it doesn't mean we should
abandon our technological development
which we already doing for many years
have both happened in parallel but it's
high time something is done about this
issue and of course these days jet
engines I mean I mean fighter planes
fifth sixth generation fighter planes
are important but we also need to in
parallel develop other systems like
drones loitering weapons and much more
drones are the future of warfare
actually drones and
Robotics geopolitical du says can France
become the next Russia for India can
trust can bat trust a colonial power
like France look France would love to
have a fully independent foreign policy
France would love to partner with a
nation like Barat in a mutually
beneficial way France would love to
genuinely be independent and Sovereign
which is which it is not because it's a
member of both NATO and the
EU uh so as long as France is a member
of NATO plus EU it's difficult for them
to truly partner with
India uh I don't care if it's a former
colonial power and all Every Nation has
done good things and bad things that's
no big deal let's not look at things
from a moralistic perspective let's look
at it from a practical and pragmatic
perspective what can they offer us if
they can offer US jet engine technology
we can purchase that they'll ask for a
high price let's pay it so uh it's it's
that sort of relationship but we have
good relations with France we have a
convergence commonality of interests in
the Indian Ocean region they have
territories there we we for us it's the
it's the home oan so it's important for
us and there's so much more
strategically that that completely
converges when it comes to France and
India the only issue is that France is a
member of NATO plus EU which means that
they are under US influence they don't
see the us as a friendly Nation by the
way but that's the constraint that they
operate under but yes if we if we play
if we take things in the right direction
it can certainly be a very beneficial
and very positive relationship both for
both Nations France won't be another
Russia for us Russia was our former
wasal uh Overlord we were the wasal in
the 19 in the
1900s but they were not an evil overload
they did not try to destroy our society
and culture and all so that won't be the
same same kind of relationship that we
will have with France but it can
definitely be a great Partnership if
things are Done
Right aniket says the Indian Navy now
wants to focus on submarines rather than
white elephant aircraft carriers what is
what is my take I say thank God thank
God sense has finally prevailed how many
times have I said we need to stop
focusing on aircraft carriers we need to
have more submarines I've been saying
saying this for four three four years
now at least over here in public I've
always
advocated more
submarines we already have X number of
aircraft carriers two of them we don't
want or need a third one why do we not
want more aircraft carriers an aircraft
carrier is the primary is is the
principal naval ship of the 20th century
we are in the 21st century the deadliest
naval ship naval asset in the world
today in the 21st century in the context
of 21st century Warfare is the
submarine the
stealthiest asset you can have and you
want distributed lethality this is a
principal basic fundamental concept of
any kind of warfare you want to
distribute your lethality over as much
territory and or as many platforms as
possible don't concentrate your
lethality on in one big platform because
that can be easily wiped out it's a
numerical game to to destroy an aircraft
carrier it's just a mathematical
certainty that if you if you if you fire
enough missiles then you will overwhelm
the
defenses and you will destroy
it and there are nations that can do it
do that even we can do that so aircraft
carriers are you know it's a nice
prestige item to have and I'm sure lots
of naval officers would love to serve on
something like like an aircraft career
but you have to be practical National
interest over godamn Prestige we need to
have lots of submarines as many as
possible I would say
5200 between 50 and 100 I know it's it's
a tremendously tall number I'm seeing
here but yeah have you seen the size of
the coast that we are defending and the
size of the maritime real estate we
claim is our strategic backyard
we need a lot of submarines we also need
to invest in missile boats for defensive
purposes rather than offensive purposes
and defense can be very rapidly turned
into offense imagine a missile boat a
small small ship that let's say carries
three brahmos and if you have 100
missile boats that's 300 brahmos brahmos
missiles that is a frightening Prospect
for anybody and that costs next to
nothing compared to last warships so
there's so much you can do if you if you
think creatively uh but coming back to
the question I'm very glad that some
some sanity and some sense has finally
prevailed and we are now going to focus
on submarines so what we need is lots of
submarines quantity has a quality of its
own instead of buying a small number of
very expensive submarines we should buy
a large number or build a large number
of relatively inexpensive submarines for
example the SW Swedish goland class
submarine let's let's Google that goland
class
submarine um let's go to
Google let's go to
gutland class submarine so this is the
Swedish Swedish go the class of
Submarine this is one of the deadliest
submarines in the world and it costs a
$100 million a
piece I assure you $100 million for a
submarine is
peanuts this thing is
deadly okay so if you're going to be a
us wasal of source we can negotiate the
the sale of the entire company to India
we will buy the entire company the
goland class submarine the parent
company will buy it and we'll move it to
India whatever it costs how about that
and then we can Mass produce the
submarines like sausages like like like
samosas why not so instead of having a
submarine that costs billion dollars to
build let's have 10 submarines Each of
which costs1
million so we have to be creative we
have to look at various Solutions and
you may ask me what's the evidence that
this submarine costs $100 million only
that's homework for you go find out how
I know that this submarine costs only
$100 million a piece homework for
you next
question Vikram Ador says how might the
moon and Mars colonization projects
affect sovereignty and jurisdictional
debates in space jurisdictional debates
are pointless who cares about debates
what matters is not a debate what
matters is the possession of territory
what matters is the creation of facts on
the ground to hell with people's debates
go debate all day all night go debate
for 10 years who cares what matters is
creating facts on the ground what
matters is the possession of territory
so yeah it will affect sovereignty
whoever sets foot first on Mars and and
creates the first Mars base will own a
chunk of a foreign of of of a of a of a
celestian object in the solar system
apart from Earth and uh I I'm pretty
sure Elon Musk will be the first king of
Mars if he is the first to reach there
he has said that he intends to die on
Mars which means that he wants to settle
down there on Mars so I'm pretty sure if
he succeeds in his Endeavors and he will
be the first king of Mars and once you
establish a colony self- sustaining
territory there you can actually declare
independence from Earth if you want to
as long as the colony is self-
sustaining eventually it will not be
possible for for long but yeah then you
will have a situation like you had
between the the between England and the
American
colonies so yeah questions of
sovereignty Etc will arise and you may
have declared cations of independence
from the Moon Moon will be difficult
because you can reach the moon pretty
quickly from Earth less than a week's
time Mars is a difficult Story the mar
is a whole different story but these
debates no one cares about debates what
matters is what facts are created on the
ground and you create facts on the
ground by
creating by by possessing and by
claiming and possessing territory on on
the
ground okay kusel kusel kandal says what
are your views on physics research on
density functional Theory I worked as an
undergraduate research assistant in El
Paso Texas on
DFT I am back to my country Bhutan now
as I've completed my studies and I'm
wondering if I should should continue
doing research in DFT or shift my focus
on string theory as you
suggested I suggested that you should
focus on string theory I am the okay I'm
not sure where you where you heard that
or who made you believe that I say that
people should focus on string theory I
am the last person to say that anyone
should focus on string theory I am one
of the harshest critics of string theory
will find anywhere in the world string
theory has proven to be a colossal waste
of monumental amounts of time and
funding string theory is a whole
gigantic exercise in in tremendous
amounts of mathematics what's the
outcome of string theory nothing zero
NADA nada what has string three produced
nothing it's produced new kinds of
mathematics good good new mathematical
techniques and all that wonderful but
what has it achieved for us in our quest
to understand the universe better
nothing whatsoever it has made no
testable predictions not
one string theory has been a waste of
time but it's somehow overhyped and it's
something that that people find
fascinating and all the funding in the
US goes to string theory if you want to
get a PhD in theoretical physics nine
times out of 10 you will have to do it
in string theory otherwise you will be
marginalized you won't get a PhD so
here's a good
cartoon look at that everyone wants to
get into String Theory but it does
nothing for physics in the real world
you want to do something that has
applications in the real world if you
want to be a productive member of
society somebody who contributes
something of value to society so I think
the answer should be very
straightforward you should focus should
continue uh focusing on DFT right so
what is DFT DFT is applied quantum
mechanics it's it's a density functional
Theory a functional is a function of a
function it's a function that takes a
function as an input and
outputs a real number of of coin so this
is sorry applied quantum mechanics uh
with DFT you investing get the
electronic structure of many body
systems like atoms molecules condensed
matter and you can study essentially
mainly ground state properties of
various condensed matter systems and DFT
has applications in the real world broad
applications in things like chemistry
Material Science in nanotechnology drug
Discovery and all and with the Advent of
machine learning and AI uh DFT becomes
even more powerful and you can make a
lot of real world difference in the real
world if you focus on DFT instead of
focusing on string theory so my
recommendation my suggestion is please
don't Focus move your focus to string
theory stay keep on researching in doing
research in
DFT all the best
sir PR Paul says Narayan morti says um
it's not ideal to follow nationalism in
today's interconnected World in a time
when Global Powers prioritize their own
national interests he
wants India to not F follow nationalism
so on whose behalf is he really batting
what could be the under L motive behind
such a statement Mr Naran morti is a
problematic individual I'll tell you
that he is a long track record of of of
funding activities that
are if not anti-india as a nation
definitely anti-indian
civilization so I'll I'll put let me put
up this
this this change.org
petition that dates back from to the
last decade about almost decade ago the
petition to remove Sheldon Pollock as
mentor and chief editor of the morti
classical Library so Naran Mor's
son U he was studying in the US and his
guide or whatever was this guy Sheldon
poock who is a known Hindu
phobe okay and he wanted to he wanted to
gain funding for translating various
Indian ancient Indian text into English
Sanskrit and other languages Sanskrit
Telugu Tamil whatnot
so pook wanted funding to do this and
the muis gave him the funding uh so this
project should be guided would be would
have to be guided and carried out by a
team of Scholars who have not only
proven Mastery in the relevant Indian
languages but are also deeply rooted and
steeped in the intellectual traditions
of India and pook is not that sort of
guy it is well well known that he has
deep antipathy towards many of the
ideals and values cherished and
practiced in our civilization he EES the
move views of mle and Marx Weber that
the shastras generated in in India serve
no contemporary purpose except for the
per study of Indians how Indians Express
themselves um there is that and U pook
is a prominent signatory of two recent
statements released by us acad
condemning the actions of the Jing
authorities in the government of India
against separatist groups who are
calling for the independence of Kashmir
and for India's breakup you know
of that sort of thing Sheldon poock
supports that and he is funded by the
mortis and he is a known Hindu phobe he
is known to have to be a person who
distorts uh the meanings of texts in his
translations in in very subtle ways so
that's the kind of anti-india virulent
India hater that the mtis have been
supporting and now he has been removed
for whatever reasons after many after
many years of of serving as a chief me
as a mentor and chief editor of this
morti classical Library that's just one
example of the activities of of of the
mortis now what I've shown you you can
look it up for
yourself they have indeed Naran morti
has definitely F funded Shon Sheldon
pook and Sheldon poock is definitely
supported anti-india activities these
are facts that you can check on your own
I'm not making hypothetical claims and
allegations these are
facts so my question is who's who who is
Mr Narayan morti batting batting for on
whose behalf definitely larger interests
are there out there probably look
everything he does it kind of aligns and
dovetails with the US agenda for for
India or against India so clearly it it
looks like he's batting for the US for
the West against us and uh he has said
it openly that he was a
leftist as a as a younger person
and he also wants Indians to work what
what 80 hours a week 100 hours I'm not
sure what what number he said that
essentially will ensure that India's TFR
drops below below any sustainable U
number because when you are overworked
and overwhelmed with stress you
cannot
procreate that's what history you over
and over again see what Christopher
Columbus does did to Hispanola to the
arak Indians he overworked the hell out
of them and they stopped reproducing and
soon enough there was complete
demographic collapse and they were
eradicated out of existence the Arawak
Indians by Christopher Columbus a
genocidal monster so if you overwork an
entire
Society the TFR declines drastically and
the society collapses so that's what Mr
morti Advocates you know it's okay for
let's say the top 1% in society to work
80 hours a week for a for a certain
period of time for two years three years
when you're pursuing a certain set of
goals but you can't do that for the rest
of your
life I would say if the ordinary Indian
uh Adult Works 40 hours a week
effectively India will be totally
transformed okay so Mr morti I don't
know what agenda he is but he definitely
has seems to have ulterior motives and
he has a track record of supporting and
funding with his own money anti- India
elements this is a fact
KP Kima says uh Namaste how should a
class 10th child like my child how
should the child study science when he
has
zero zero interest in it you always
encourage people to learn science he
said he says it doesn't want to study
because that's pointless I do encourage
people to learn science yes but I know
that some people don't like science and
the constant science so you cannot force
science on everybody you can't just like
you cannot force
arts on everybody some people just do
can't do arts right my point is it's not
for everybody and if a kid has zero
interest like you say and you you are
the mother so you will know very well
then please don't force science on the
kid just ensure that he or she um he
it's a he just ensure that he just
studies enough to pass the exam or
whatever it is and then let him go into
his into whatever field he prefers arts
arts or or or or Commerce or whatever
science is not for everyone I would love
for everyone to be uh decently good at
science but it's not for everyone so
don't please don't force your kid it's
going to be
counterproductive don't don't do that
all right all the
best John Cena says what advice would
you give can you give to a 25y old guy
who is now broke he has dreamed of
becoming an entrepreneur since his 20s
but since he was 20 but because of
family conditions and other reasons he
procrastinated he completed engineering
and computer computer science good and
worked it job for 2 years then he took a
risk at 24 and left his job to start his
own startup and now he has lost all his
savings and he's feeling depressed first
thing I would say first thing never feel
sorry for yourself and waste time crying
tears for how terrible your situation is
it's for losers get the hell
up get get up on your feet second you
have
certain assets that very few people have
you have uh skills in computer science
you have experience in
these are valuable assets okay you took
a risk and you failed in your startup
boohoo so what does it mean you're a bad
person does it mean you're a failure
you're 25 you're starting off in life
reframe your mindset reframe your
orientation reframe your worldview you
don't succeed before you fail multiple
times it's a very small minority of
people to succeed right from the
beginning to really succeed in life you
have to have failed over and over again
look at the biography of any great
person more failures than
success so stop feeling sorry for
yourself in case you're feeling that
way uh you're feeling depressed which
means you're feeling sorry enough of
that get get up on your feet um okay you
broke so the first thing you need is
money so go apply for
jobs spend a couple of years more
working saving money and then in the
meanwhile try and analyze is what
contributed to the failure of your
startup learn the lessons from it and
then once you are in a better place
mentally and and financially you can try
that again or try a different kind of
startup or try a different venture or
maybe spend a few few more years working
getting a salary and saving look the
future is open all possibilities are
open for you my advice is be positive
don't waste time feeling sorry for
yourself depression you know what solve
what cures
depression you get out of your
house you stay indoors in your room
you're going to be depressed get the
hell out of the house go for a 1our walk
somewhere go in the forest go go on the
streets wherever go walk think look
around activity destroys depression
movement destroys
depression so be positive you have
valuable assets you have skills you have
experience
leverage that go apply for jobs again
you will get a job somewhere or the
other spend some year some spend some
time earning money again and then
everything is fine then you can do you
can stay in a job or you can maybe start
a new startup if you want everything's
possible but don't waste your time
feeling sorry for yourself take action
get going get moving all right sir all
the
best okay let's take some questions from
the live chat shall
we uh Ang tripati says this is not live
it's just a
recording if it's a recording how am I
reacting to what what you're saying here
bro is not recording is very much live
yes
sir all right all right now now let's
take some
questions
uh uh yes davic davic shrien says
Manipur CM Mr bin Singh has just
resigned what can I make from this it's
too early to say anything it happened a
couple of hours ago it happened earlier
today right the resignation of of Mr bin
Singh so I don't know what to make from
it he I think he was in Delhi yesterday
he met he met with Mr Amit sha and today
he has resigned so the next phase of the
situation in Manipur evolves now uh I
don't it's too early for me to react to
anything uh we'll have to wait and watch
uh what happens
now is the BJP going to impose president
rule president's rule in a state it
itself governs or are they going to
appoint a new chief Minister if there's
going to be a new chief minister who is
going to
be and then what are the new policies
that are going to be implemented if any
all that we have to see so let's wait
and watch it's too early to give a
knee-jerk
reaction but yeah interesting uh
development that is happening that is
happening um
okay let's take some few more questions
Mr long
stong says how do we overcome this North
versus South divide for good well I have
certain radical steps that I can propose
but I will not do that
because because one doesn't say such
things the thing is
this look who is creating this north
south divide the people haven't created
this divide it is the
politicians and some politicians who are
doing it they have created this divide
for their own benefit
just like this cast divide it is the
politicians who have imposed cast on
India they force you to have cast on all
your certificates your birth certificate
your school certificate and so on so
forth all government documents cast has
to be there remove it cast is over we
were never the sort of society the
government has ensured cast is has
become a thing a real thing and
similarly this north south divide or
whatever East West divide it's
politicians who do it they want to keep
you divided so that they can keep repe
benefits from that
electorally so what needs to be done in
a democratic system you'll have to
tolerate such nonsense so we need a
better
system we need a better system a better
political system for India which is more
suited to the kind of entity the Indian
civilization state
is um the the the the problem is certain
politicians and certain political
parties I'm not naming anybody but that
is the problem so the solution then
becomes self-apparent
that once we don't have such politicians
and political entities on the scene then
these divides will eventually slowly
disappear so for that to happen we need
a different political
system a more centralized let's say a
presidential system and uh maybe a
different Constitution maybe a different
set of laws uh big ask
big
ask Sid says should the PM ask for
access to Advanced Nvidia AI chips and
some tech sharing us has placed some
restrictions on India due to Biden's
chips act I
guess well we can ask for it will they
give it is a different story I me you
ask them for the keys to the kingdom
will they give it there'll be some
technology they will never share with
anybody okay uh but yes there's no harm
in asking for
it no harm at
all trti P says that I am not human I'm
just a robot no ma'am I'm I'm in Ai No
not an AI
alien uh vicam geopolitical says why did
the US discontinu the F22 Raptor in my
view it's superior to the F35 in my view
also the F22 is the best aircraft ever
built probably one of the one of the
best aircrafts ever built definitely the
best aircraft the Americans have it's
definitely superior to the F35 I have no
idea why they have discontinued it no
idea it makes no sense for them to
discontinue an aircraft of that caliber
and that that you know that good an
aircraft doesn't make sense maybe they
are building continuing to build it in
secret I'm not sure doesn't make sense
to discontinue the best thing you've
built abov Bal courot says
how come Nordic nations are number one
in happiness index as well as number one
in suicide
rates well there you go there you go it
tells you how hypocritical and
nonsensical these indices are the
happiness index is propaganda it's it's
Western propaganda that's all it is how
can you have the highest suicide rates
and also be the happiest nation in the
world makes no sense whatsoever it tells
you these indices cannot be trusted they
cannot be you should not take them
seriously it's merely
propaganda okay what other I can take a
couple more questions mclen says we are
having a lot of meetings with Bhutan is
there something
cooking well I cannot tell you about
it definitely you're right lots of
meetings the the king of Bhutan comes
here every couple of months um the
defense Minister comes and meets our
defense minister something is cooking
perhaps but what it is well who knows
who
knows Brides says coaching centers like
iits for for I Etc are becoming suicide
centers why is the government of India
not taking action because it's a huge
industry the the education industry is a
huge industry with lots of entrench
interests and U where this huge amount
of money you have political interests in
all and it's just the way it is so uh
look this this is all wrong what's
happening in India right the entire
education system I've spoken about it at
length it's rotten it is it's it's
useless for the country it doesn't give
us what it's supposed to give so in my
opinion the whole system has to be
revamped why is the government not doing
it I don't
know and I'm not going to shed any more
tears over that
they're not doing it they're not doing
it there's nothing I can do about it
so but you right it's it's terrible it's
terrible so much pressure on young kids
it's it's absolutely terrible and it's a
tragedy when a young young child uh
young young person you know feels so
cornered and option lless they they feel
that it's easier to just Escape in this
manner it's terrible it's
terrible
okay um
Amisha says why do we dream and do you
believe in reincarnation I don't know
about reincarnation okay I don't there's
no evidence scientific scientific
evidence about reincarnation but is it
possible well one can have an open mind
about that so I'm agnostic about it I
would say why do we dream uh we're not
quite sure why we dream there are
various theories one theory is that uh
dreaming makes helps our mind brain make
sense of information and reconfigure
information while we sleep okay so we
have experiences during our waking hours
but we sleep let's say roughly eight
hours a day on average for the average
person and during that that sleep period
is very important for our mind for our
brain because the brain needs that if
you deprive a person of sleep for for a
certain number of days you can even die
that person can even die and uh that
person will die if you deprive that
person of sleep for an extended extended
period of time 7 10 days uh so the brain
needs sleep and sleep is extremely
important for for the brain's
functioning why we don't quite know but
one theory is that we the brain
reconfigures memories and experiences
and puts them in the right places and
makes connections with previous
experiences Etc and this manifests
itself in the form of dreams and some
once again there are recurring dreams
and all which don't quite make sense and
all so we don't quite know very well the
brain is the least understood organ of
the body the mind is is even less
understood in Consciousness it's a
mystery uh yeah so very deep and
profound question you've asked but the
scientific world doesn't have clear
answers for these things it tells you
how little we understand of our own mind
in our
body and with amish's question I'm going
to end today's live stream lots of more
questions but it's time to end it for
today thank you everybody for all the
questions and we'll do this once again
next week all right until then until
then take care keep asking questions and
keep raising your stands see you soon
bye